ACTWU's Rieve-Pollock Foundation Records 5619/008
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ACTWU's Rieve-Pollock Foundation Records
1935-1996
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union. Rieve-Pollock Foundation
Textile Workers' Union of America. Rieve-Pollock Foundation
5619/008
4.25 cubic feet
4.3 linear feet
Correspondence, reports, publications.
This collection consists of correspondence, reports, minutes of directors' meetings, and files from the Rieve-Pollack Foundation. The bulk of the collection dates from the years 1935-1996. Some of the records, however are from as early as 1926 and as late as 1999, thus a few of the records are from the UNITE era.
6764535
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
Date completed:
February 17, 2010
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, July 2010
Biographical / Historical
The Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, the most significant union representing workers in the men's clothing industry, was founded in New York City in 1914 as a breakaway movement from the United Garment Workers. Radical and immigrant workers in the tailors' and cutters' locals were the core of the seceding group, which advocated industrial unionism and economic strikes in opposition to the UGW's craft organization, which they saw as conservative and timid. Their diverging views had come to the fore during the historic 1910 dispute at the Chicago firm Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. The opposition called the strike against the UGW leadership's advice, and reached a path-breaking agreement with management that established an arbitration system to settle disputes.
Members flocked to the new union. Around 50,000 strong at its founding, by 1920 the ACWA counted about 170,000 members. Initially composed mostly of immigrants of Jewish European descent with Socialist leanings, the ACWA quickly welcomed members of a great number of nationalities and diverse backgrounds. Like in other garment unions, most workers and many members were women, but the leadership was predominantly male, a situation that did not change for many decades. Early on the union adopted a centralized administrative structure combined with industrial unionism, with the joint boards' by-laws having precedence over those of locals.
Espousing a philosophy perhaps brought over by its early immigrant socialist members, the Amalgamated went beyond bread and butter issues and adopted a distinctive form of social unionism that was largely absent in the American labor movement. Starting in the 1920s, it provided educational opportunities and recreational facilities for its members, as well as services such as an insurance plan, banks offering personal loans at low interest rates, low-cost housing cooperatives, medical clinics, and even union-owned restaurants.
Sidney Hillman was the first president of the new union and the most important officer in its history. He applied his experience as bargaining representative in Chicago to the whole industry. Under his leadership the union made significant strides in securing better wages and working conditions for its members, and at the same time it consolidated gains and provided stability to the industry through the widespread adoption of the arbitration system tested at Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. Hillman paid close attention to industry issues, such as production, pricing, and marketing. In order to help management meet the competition of non-union firms, the union conducted studies of efficiency, work methods, and factory costs. Letters to the official publication of the union, Advance, document the controversy that ensued within the union over what was perceived to be collaboration with management.
Hillman also understood the importance of labor's involvement in national affairs and political action. In the 1920s the ACWA sent delegates to the Conference for Progressive Political Action and to the Farmer-labor party conventions. Although many members and officers were Socialists, the union stopped short of officially endorsing the party. Communist attempts at gaining influence within the union were firmly curbed. Hillman's participation in national affairs and politics became prominent during the New Deal, when he became a close advisor to Franklin D. Roosevelt on labor and economic issues. He also served on the board of the National Recovery Administration. Later, during World War II, he helped establish the Labor's Non Partisan League. He was also named associate director of the Office of Production Management, which assisted in mobilizing the nation's resources for the war effort. Hillman's prestige perhaps reflected the healthy condition of his union, which by the end of the conflict was strong and stable.
During the post World War II period the union faced a number of significant challenges. Membership continued to grow (peaking at 395,000 in 1968), but the union's political influence and visibility in national affairs declined. In their never ending pursuit of lower production costs, many firms relocated to the South, forcing the union to engage in large organizing efforts. Simultaneously, signs began to appear of changes that would lead to the almost complete demise of the domestic apparel industry and, ultimately, to the erosion of union membership. Foreign imports of cheap clothing goods steadily grew in the 1950s and 1960s, and mushroomed in the following two decades, plunging employment in the apparel sector into a steady decline. Union efforts to stem the tide included Buy American campaigns and extensive lobbying in Congress, but they were to no avail. In 1976, the ACWA merged with the Textile Workers of America to become the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union. Despite successful and much publicized nationwide actions such as the Farah boycott and the J.P. Stevens corporate campaign, the woes threatening the union's existence continued unabated. The fate of the domestic industry was sealed in the late 1970s and the 1980s by the flight of firms chasing tax breaks and cheap labor abroad. By 1995, when ACTWU voted to merge with the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, their combined membership was 350,000. The new Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE!) seemed poised to infuse new life in a troubled union.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related collections: 5619: Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America And all other 5619 collections.
Textile industry -- New York (State) -- New York; Textile workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Clothing trade -- New York (State) -- New York; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union; Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America; Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America. Rieve-Pollock Foundation; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; Textile Workers Union of America; Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees; UNITE HERE (Organization)
6764535
- 9/7/89 Rieve-Pollock, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  September 7, 1989.
- Rieve-Pollock, 1977-1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Rieve-Pollock, 1993-1996 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Larry Rogin, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Rieve-Pollock Finances, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Moses Finley, 1986-1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- UNITE Monica Russo, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- ACTOR N. Miami Beach, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- The Honor of Labor Exhibit-Scalamandre Silk Mill Report, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Local 1733 Sol Stetin Administrator, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Ed Katz, 1981-1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Textile History, 1937-1991 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Rieve-Pollock Foundation, 1935-1996 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Uprising of 1934 [1934 Strike] (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Southern Labor Management Dinner- 2/6/82, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  February 6, 1982.
- Knitwear Workers 36th Conference, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- 1979 Program from Waldorf Astoria (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Rieve-Pollock 10th Anniversary (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Pictures, 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Sol Stetin Remarks. 50th Anniversary TWUA, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Midwest Conference 6/5/82, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  June 5, 1982.
- Sol Stetin- Miscellaneous Honors, 1982-1993 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Miscellaneous Papers, 1949-1992 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Uprising of 1934 [1934 Strike] (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Sol Stetin. Citizen of Patterson, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Sol Stetin. Speeches, Addresses, 1982-1989 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Rieve-Pollock. Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1976-1994 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Joseph L. Hueter, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Retiree Programs, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Press Stories, 1956-1993 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- ACTWU/UNITE Biographies (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Union Scholarships, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Botto House Labor Museum, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Rieve-Pollock Newsletter, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Rieve-Pollock Corporate Records (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Book #1 Final Report, Cumulative Index, Barkin, Benet, Boggs (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Book #2 Cook, Fiester, Gordon, Hueter (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Book #3 Perkel, Rogin, Rogin & Fiester, Schaufenbil, Tibbets (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Book #4 Stetin, Swaity, Todd, Williams, Watson (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Deep South L-M Dinner, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Friday, February 6, 1982. Atlanta Georgia
- New England Region Luncheon, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Saturday, April 17, 1982-Boston
- Greater Toronto Joint Board-Annual Dinner and Meeting, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  March 27, 1982.
- Quin State Dinner in Honor of Sol Stetin, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Saturday, May 22, 1982. Philadelphia
- Southwest Ontario Joint Board, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Saturday, April 24,1982-Ontario
- "Why Sol Stetin Stepped Down" Nation, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  December 10, 1977.
- Smithsonian Institute Speech (Box 2, Folder 7)
  November 16, 199?
- Rieve-Pollock Foundation. General, 1981-1993 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Sol Stetin-Bergen Record. J.P. Stevens, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  August 9, 1979.
- Post Merger Material, 1937-1995 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Sol Stetin. Biography, 1968-1986 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Mike Stetson, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Sol Stetin Banquet, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  October 13, 1979. Miscellaneous Correspondence
- Sol Stetin, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  October 16, 1979. Banquet, Letters of Congratulation
- Sol Stetin. Personal Correspondence, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- William Patterson College of New Jersey, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  July 16, 1979.
- Great Falls Development Corporation. General, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- TWUA Publications, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Chronology of Textile Workers Union of America, 1934-1976 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Rubenstein Data, 1945-1977 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Jack Rubenstein, 1935-1977 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- NO Label, 1926-1972 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Rubenstein Data, 1946-1976 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Rubenstein Files from Dyers Federation [folder 1 of 3], 1935-1989 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Rubenstein Files from Dyers Federation [folder 2 of 3], 1934-1938 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Rubenstein Files from Dyers Federation [folder 3 of 3], 1935-1989 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Official Seal of the Rieve-Pollock Foundation (Box 2)
- 1934 Textile Strike, An Introduction to a Proposed Film Producer Vera Rony (Box 2)
  Video
- Rieve-Pollock Foundation-10th Anniversary Conference, 1986 (Box 2)
  October 26, 1986. Video
- TWUA Organizing Campaign in South (Late 40's or Early 50's) and TWUA Convention (Box 2)
- Rieve-Pollock Foundation Conference-Gaithersburg, MD Tape 1, 1989 (Box 2)
  November 18, 1989. Video
- Rieve-Pollock Foundation Conference-Gaithersburg, MD Tape 2, 1989 (Box 2)
- Directors Meeting, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  March 20, 1978.
- Directors Meeting, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  February 8, 1972.
- Directors Meeting, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  January 29, 1980.
- Directors Meeting, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  June 3, 1980.
- Directors Meeting, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  November 6, 1980.
- Directors Meeting, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  April 1, 1981.
- Directors Meeting, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  August 14, 1981.
- Directors Meeting, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  April 13, 1982.
- Directors Meeting, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  June 24, 1982.
- Directors Meeting, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  June 28, 1983.
- Directors Meeting, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  July 25, 1984.
- Directors Meeting, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  June 7, 1985.
- Directors Meeting, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  December 18, 1985.
- Directors Meeting, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  July 17, 1986.
- Directors Meeting, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  March 24, 1987.
- Directors Meeting, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  March 29, 1988.
- Directors Meeting, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  May 19, 1989.
- Directors Meeting, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  June 20, 1989.
- Directors Meeting, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  January 9, 1990.
- Directors Meeting, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  May 21, 1990.
- Directors Meeting, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  July 23, 1990.
- Directors Meeting, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  August 22, 1990.
- Directors Meeting, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  May 20, 1991.
- Directors Meeting, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  August 26, 1991.
- Directors Meeting, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  November 26, 1991.
- Directors Meeting. Cancelled, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  April 23, 1993.
- Directors Meeting, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  February 15, 1996.
- Directors Meeting, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  January 29, 1997.
- 1934 General Strike Conference-Philadelphia, PA, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  November 10, 1984.
- 10th Anniversary Celebration-Washington, DC, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  October 25-26, 1986.
- Conference-Gaithersburg, MD, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  November 19, 1988.
- Conference-NY, NY 9/30/90 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Conference-Gaithersburg, MD, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  November 13-14, 1993.
- American Woolen Mills (Vermont Project), 1990-1993 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Cooleemee Historical Society Project (Harold Foster Papers), 1989-1992 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Darlington Project, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- NYS Labor History Association-Labor Landmarks Map/Poster Project, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Operation Dixie History Project, 1984-1989 (Box 3, Folder 38)
- 1928 New Bedford-Fall River Strike Project, 1989-1995 (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Scalamandre Silks Photo Project, 1982-1989 (Box 3, Folder 40)
- JP Stevens History Project (James Hodges), 1986-1992 (Box 3, Folder 41)
- Textile Song Project (Joe Glazer)-Textile Voices, Songs from the Mill, 1984-1995 (Box 3, Folder 42)
- George Waldrep Research Project, 1993-1996 (Box 3, Folder 43)
- New England Textile Industry-William Hartford, 1991-1996 (Box 3, Folder 44)
- Sol Barkin Book Purchase, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 45)
- Hoyman Book Donation, 1986-1991 (Box 3, Folder 46)
- Rieve-Pollock Foundation, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 47)
- Rieve-Pollock Foundation, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 48)
- Rieve-Pollock Foundation, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 49)
- Barbara Kopple's American Dream Film, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 50)
- Honea Path Memorial Fund, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 51)
- Michelle Brattain PhD Dissertation, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 52)
- "Southern Exposure" Article on JP Stevens, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 53)
- TWUA Presidents Room-99 University Place, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 54)
- Rieve-Pollock Foundation Programs, 1976-1982 (Box 3, Folder 55)
- Rieve-Pollock Foundation Slide Show-"Our Lives, Our Rights", 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 56)
- Rieve-Pollock Foundation Organizational Records-Procedures, 1976-1983 (Box 3, Folder 57)
- Bob Bussel Grant Request, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 58)
- N.E.H Grant Proposal for TWUA History, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 59)
- TWUA History Grant Applications, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 60)
- TWUA History (Daniel), 1946-1999 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Botto House American Labor Museum, 1982-1996 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Rieve-Pollock Foundation Retiree Newsletter, 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- 1934 Textile Strike Project-Vera Rony-1977-1987 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- "Uprising of '34" 1934 Strike Film (Vera Rony) [folder 1 of 2], 1982-1996 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- 1934 Strike Film (Vera Rony), 1990-1995 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Rieve-Pollock FoundationWilliam Du Chessi Scholarship Fund, 1979-1989 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Rieve-Pollock Foundation-William Du Chessi Scholarship Fund, 1990-1997 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Rieve-Pollock Foundation Finances, 1977-1984 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Rieve-Pollock Foundation Finances, 1977-1997 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Reports to Government Agencies Tax Forms 990 EZ & Exemption Form, 1978-1995 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Oversize-Original Charters (Box 5, Folder 1)